Guide to the Everett Cherrington Hughes Papers 1922-1982
University of Chicago Library
- Series VII: Helen MacGill Hughes (1903-1992)
  - Milofsky, Carl, "Good People and Dirty Work Revisited: The Diffusion of Responsibility in School Psychology," manuscript, 1978 (Box 137, Folder 9)
  - Weiss, Robert, "Third Meeting at Stockbridge School," manuscript, 1969 (Box 137, Folder 10)
- Series VIII: Audio-Visual Materials
  Series VIII contains reel-to-reel and cassette tapes that consist of lectures, dictated letters, and memoranda. The single roll of microfilm was made in 1960 by Helen MacGill Hughes of the manuscript prepared for Fantastic Lodge: The Autobiography of a Girl Drug Addict (1961). Hughes dictated many of his letters and memoranda on to dictadisks for transcription by a secretary. The dictadisk subseries is divided into dictadisks without transcripts and dictadisks with transcripts. The arrangement of these sub subseries mirrors the organization of the entire collection.
  The reel-to-reel and cassette tapes as well as the microfilm in this series are restricted due to their fragile condition or need for special equipment.
  - Subseries 1: Reel-to-reel, 7"
    - Brandeis University, Sociology 118a, "Social Institutions," lectures, October 1961-December 1961 (Box 138, Folder 1-7)
    - Brandeis University, Sociology 227a, "Seminar on Occupations," lectures, October 1964-November 1964 (Box 138, Folder 8-12)
    - Brandeis University, Sociology 227a, "Seminar on Occupations," lectures, November 1964-January 1965 (Box 139, Folder 1-5)
    - Meeting at the Statler Hilton, August 27, 1963 (Box 139, Folder 6)
    - Side 1: Cayton on Hughes talk, October 23, 1963; Side 2: Hughes, Presidential Address, August 1963, This item has been reformatted for access. (Box 139, Folder 7)
    - Horace Cayton, "Beyond the Black Metropolis," about Dick Wright, Robert Park and Louis Wirth, November 4, 1963 (Box 139, Folder 8)
    - Speech on race relations at meeting of the Eastern Region of the Sociological Society, 1969 (Box 139, Folder 9)
    - Memo on mobility of colleges, n.d. (Box 139, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, n.d. (Box 139, Folder 11)
    - Discussion, n.d. (Box 139, Folder 12)
  - Subseries 2: Reel-to-reel, 3"
    - Correspondence, n.d. (Box 140, Folder 1-4)
    - Notes on the clothing of women in Florence, memorandum, n.d. (Box 140, Folder 5)
    - Memo about talk given on professions, n.d. (Box 140, Folder 6)
    - Memo about parents not understanding their children's choice of profession, n.d. (Box 140, Folder 7)
    - Notes on education, n.d. (Box 140, Folder 8)
    - unidentified; unintelligible, n.d. (Box 140, Folder 9)
  - Subseries 3: Microfilm
    - The Fantastic Lodge: the Autobiography of a Girl Addict, manuscript, correspondence, 1960 (Box 140, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 4: Cassettes
    - Sociology in Canada, memorandum, n.d. (Box 140, Folder 11)
    - Field work in Canada, memorandum, n.d. (Box 140, Folder 12)
    - Thoughts on the referendum to separate Quebec from Canada, memorandum, n.d. (Box 140, Folder 13)
    - Memories of Sidney Spivak, memorandum, n.d. (Box 140, Folder 14)
    - Thoughts on the relationship between languages, races, nations and states, memorandum, September 23, 1977 (Box 140, Folder 15)
    - unidentified, broken tape, n.d. (Box 140, Folder 16)
  - Subseries 5: Dictadisks without transcripts
    - Sub-subseries 1: Correspondence
      - American Medical Association, November 1966 American Sociological Association, n.d. B, general, C. D. Bryant, October 1969 Brandeis University, sit-ins, 1969 Brandeis University, Department of Sociology, April 1970 Bramson, Leon, n.d. Burgess, Ernest W., n.d. C, general, Joseph M. Cronin, March 1970 C, general, Mickey K. Clampit, March 1970 Daedalus, general, 1964-1965 Evans, Thomas C., November 1969 Evans, Thomas C., May 1970 Foote, Nelson N., January 1970 Geer, Blanche, June 1970 Goffman, Erving, December 1978 J, general, n.d. K, general, Judith Kramer, June 1970 LaPierre and Olivier, n.d. (Box 141, Folder 1)
      - Lee, Shu-Ching, December 1969 M, general, Mackey, William F., June 1970 Reisman, David, [1969] S, general, n.d. S, general, comments on Alice Stewart's thesis, October 1969 Thorne, Barrie, n.d. University of Toronto, n.d. University of Washington, Robert E. L. Varis, n.d. W, general, Dennis Wrong, n.d. (Box 141, Folder 2)
    - Sub-subseries 2: Course WorkóStudent Work
      - Laurin, Nicole, n.d. (Box 141, Folder 3)
    - Sub-subseries 3: Writings and Research
      - Conversation with BrÈton, n.d. Conversation with Craig, June 1965 Conversation with Dufresne, n.d. Conversation with Hallen, 1968 Foundation Man project, notes, 1968 Ryan, C., July 1965 Medicine in Quebec, letter to Professor Lewis Killian, n.d. "MÈmoir de M. Hughes au sujet de la situation de Canada au moment actuel," September 1965 Canadian Convocation talks, May-June, 1969 Research material, race relations in Europe, memorandum, 1969 Memorial to Ernest Burgess, n.d. Juneau, July 13, n.d. "Town-Gown in the Professor," n.d. Trudeau, CollËge des mÈdicins, July 28, n.d. Memoranda, September 1965 Memorandum, March 14, n.d. Memoranda, June 10, 11, n.d. Confidential memo, n.d. Notes, n.d. Unidentified, n.d. (Box 141, Folder 4)
    - Sub-subseries 4: French Canada Studies--Royal Commission on Bilingualism and Biculturalism
      - Administration, Pierre Gauthier (2) Administration, personnel, correspondence, 1964 Administration, report, September 8, 1965 Administration, Margaret Westley, 1965 (3) Administration, Margaret Westley, SÈguin, McGill University Memorandum, May 6, 1965 Memorandum, n.d. Imperial Tobacco, memorandum, ca. 1965 Labour College, memorandum, ca. 1965 (Box 141, Folder 5)
    - Sub-subseries 5: University of Kansas Medical and General Education Studies
      - Interviews with Cadieux and Hall, ca. 1960 Geer, Blanche, correspondence, 1960 (Box 141, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 6: Dictadisks with transcripts
    - Japan and Korea trip, July 16-20, 1962 Japan, July 21-28, 1962 Japan, July 29-August 1, 1962 Japan, August 3-7, 1962 Japan, August 8, 1962 (Box 141, Folder 7)
    - Japan, August 10-11, 1962 Japan, August 14-21, 1962 Third World Conference on Medical Education, New Delhi, India, November 1966 Sociological meeting, Tougaloo, Mississippi, March 1964 Confidential notes on Boston College, October 15, December 8, 1968 Notes on the University of Alabama, Tuscaloosa, November 1968 Visit to Cedar Crest College, February 18, 1969 Repatriation of Immigrants and on Racialism in Britain, June 22, 1969 French Canada, memorandum, August 12, 1969 French Canada, memorandum, March 20, 1970 (Box 141, Folder 8)
- Series IX: Letters of Reference, Grant Evaluations, and Referee Reports
  Arranged alphabetically, this series consists of recommendations for students and colleagues, a few grant proposal evaluations, and a few referee reports for papers in the field of sociology. Series IX is restricted and unavailable for research until 2030.
  - General, A-B, 1949-1980 (Box 142, Folder 1)
  - General, C, 1959-1976 (Box 142, Folder 2)
  - General, D, 1961-1979 (Box 142, Folder 3)
  - General, E-F, 1941-1974 (Box 142, Folder 4)
  - General, G, 1953-1974 (Box 142, Folder 5)
  - General, H, 1946-1979 (Box 142, Folder 6)
  - General, I-K, 1954-1973 (Box 142, Folder 7)
  - General, L, 1945-1976 (Box 142, Folder 8)
  - General, M, 1951-1977 (Box 142, Folder 9)
  - General, N-O, 1963-1976 (Box 143, Folder 1)
  - General, P, 1963-1975 (Box 143, Folder 2)
  - General, R, 1953-1978 (Box 143, Folder 3)
  - General, Sa-Sm, 1959-1976 (Box 143, Folder 4)
  - General, So-Sz, 1960-1975 (Box 143, Folder 5)
  - General, T, 1952-1977 (Box 143, Folder 6)
  - General, U-W, 1952-1973 (Box 143, Folder 7)
  - General, Y-Z, 1962-1978 (Box 143, Folder 8)
  - Allon Harris, Natalie, 1969-1978 (Box 143, Folder 9)
  - American Journal of Sociology, 1965-1974 (Box 143, Folder 10)
  - American Journal of Sociology, 1975 (Box 144, Folder 1)
  - American Sociological Review, 1973-1974 (Box 144, Folder 2)
  - Anderson, Nels, 1963 (Box 144, Folder 3)
  - Bodeman, Michael, 1967-1974 (Box 144, Folder 4)
  - Cahnman, Werner, 1961-1973 (Box 144, Folder 5)
  - Campanis, Paul, 1966-1969 (Box 144, Folder 6)
  - Geer, Blanche, 1978 (Box 144, Folder 7)
  - Henry, William, 1963 (Box 144, Folder 8)
  - Hill, Mozel, 1957 (Box 144, Folder 9)
  - MacDonnell, Allan, 1971 (Box 144, Folder 10)
  - MassÈ, Jacqueline, 1962-1964 (Box 144, Folder 11)
  - Mogey, John, 1963-1976 (Box 144, Folder 12)
  - National Science Foundation, 1967-1977 (Box 144, Folder 13)
  - Nelson, Leona, 1956-1964 (Box 144, Folder 14)
  - Noorani, Saleem, 1969 (Box 144, Folder 15)
  - Ostow, Robin, 1972-1976 (Box 144, Folder 16)
  - Riesman, David, 1949-1973 (Box 144, Folder 17)
  - Rossi, Peter H., 1956 (Box 144, Folder 18)
  - Roth, Julius, 1954-1968 (Box 144, Folder 19)
  - Thorne, Barrie, 1968-1969 (Box 144, Folder 20)
  - United States Government, Department of Health, Education and Welfare, 1967 (Box 144, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous journals, 1969-1976 (Box 144, Folder 22)
- Series X: Oversize
  - Germany, Catholic labor movement, 12 Kongress der Christlichen Gewerkschaften Deutschlands, September 15-18, 1929 (Box 145, Folder 1)
  - Germany, World War II propaganda, map of Germany and Poland, September and December 1939 (Box 145, Folder 2)
  - French-Canada and the War, American and Canadian broadsides, newspaper clippings 1940-1944 (Box 145, Folder 3)
  - Germany, rise of the Nazi party, American newspaper, Das Neue Deutschland," 1933 (Box 145, Folder 4)
  - Germany, rise of the Nazi party, American newspaper, miscellaneous, 1932-1933, 1939 (Box 145, Folder 5)
  - Germany, rise of the Nazi party, British newspaper, Manchester Guardian, 1933 (Box 145, Folder 6)
  - Germany, rise of the Nazi party, German newspapers, Berliner Illustriete Nachtausgabe, 1932 (Box 146, Folder 1)
  - Germany, rise of the Nazi party, German newspapers, Berliner Zeitung am Mittag, 1932 (Box 146, Folder 2-3)
  - Germany, rise of the Nazi party, German newspapers, Der Angriff, Berlin, 1932 (Box 146, Folder 4-5)
  - Germany, rise of the Nazi party, German newspapers, Der Deutsche, Berlin, 1929, 1932 (Box 146, Folder 6)
  - Germany, rise of the Nazi party, German newspapers, Berliner Tageblatt, 1933 (Box 146, Folder 7)
  - Germany, rise of the Nazi party, German newspapers, miscellaneous, July 2, 1933 (Box 146, Folder 8)
  - Germany, rise of the Nazi party, German newspapers, miscellaneous, 1931-1932 (Box 146, Folder 9)
  - Germany, rise of the Nazi party, German newspapers, miscellaneous, 1933-1934 (Box 146, Folder 10)
  - Third World Conference on medical Education, Participation Certificate, 1966 (Box 146, Folder 11)
  - Germany, rise of the Nazi party, German newspapers, Frankfurter Zeitung, 1932 (Box 147, Folder 1-3)
  - Germany, rise of the Nazi party, German newspapers, Frankfurter Zeitung, 1933 (Box 147, Folder 4-5)
  - Germany, rise of the Nazi party, German newspapers, Frankfurter Zeitung, 1934 (Box 147, Folder 6)
  - Germany, rise of the Nazi party, German newspapers, Saarsbrücker Zeitung, December 1933 (Box 147, Folder 7)
  - Germany, rise of the Nazi party, American and Canadian newspapers, miscellaneous, 1931-1934 (Box 147, Folder 8)